We call the order of the regular scheduled minimum city council for Tuesday, June 21st, 2020.
Public input on schedule personal expenses, and then three consent agenda staff recommends we approve out of four and five.
Is that not, don't go high, Parker.
Okay, six presentation from my academic development services. Mr. Chan, do you want?
Good evening, council. Mayor.
I'll do my best to keep this under an hour.
That was a joke.
First of all, I want to start by to say thank you for allowing me to be here tonight to speak to you.
Just to kind of give you some updates on where we are with the Miami Air Economic Development Service,
some things we're going to be working on.
If you remember in May, heaven-niller, one of our board members was here,
and I was here to update and tune on some of the strategic initiatives that the main board was working on prior to becoming all board June 6.
And among those, those items were business retention and development expansion, workforce development,
recruitment of new business, collaboration with airing and municipalities, county and tribal governments,
revenue growth and marketing and branding.
And so there's been a lot to talk about.
You know, Dr. Stafford has a main cost to have to remember the main board.
Talked a lot about, you know, he doesn't like to turn the bays.
Because he thinks every time he hears that word, he thinks we're a cleaning company.
And so he's really trying to get everyone away from using that term.
And to talk more specifically about, we're a economic development service.
That's what we are. That's who we are.
Because it's hard to define bays and people are already thinking cleaning company.
So one of the things that I thought might be good today is just to talk a little bit about what is economic development.
And what it is we do at the economic development service.
And so one of the things about economic development is that it's an investment in growing our economy
with the ultimate goal of enhancing the prosperity and quality of life for all residents.
That's what we're here for.
That's what you try to do as a council.
You try to do things to better position the city of Miami.
so that you can provide better quality services for your residents.
You try to do your best to improve the climate in the city of Miami,
to make it easier to do business hopefully with the city of Miami.
Because the next thing is economic development,
really focuses on the allocation of limited resources.
None of us have a finite supply of land, labor, or capital.
There's only so much of it that you as a city can develop,
or to our devote to economic development.
There's only so much we can do as the economic development service.
There's only so much our tribal partners can do in our other musical partners in the county.
And the whole point is to get everybody on the same page working together
to bring about economic development.
For you as a city, you can look at us really kind of as an extension of what you do here,
and look at us as kind of your unofficial economic development department.
Because you are without a doubt one of the bigger investors into the economic development service.
Both through your donation of the money that you think the rural cash are that the funds
that you allocate to the organization and through the utility credits that you extend to the organization as well.
That adds up to a good deal of money and resources to help fund economic development.
So when we do things out in the economic development world, we are doing those things on your behalf.
We are working as an extension of the city.
The same thing would apply as we work with the other municipalities, as we work with the county,
and we work with build relationships with our tribal partners.
It's the same concept. Everybody invest.
We are there to serve all of you to help bring about and improve the economy here in Ottawa County.
That's our focus.
So when you talk about the benefits of economic development,
really it's about your community vision.
And it's about taking that vision that dream, what you want for economic development,
what you want for a strong vibrant economy in Miami and in Ottawa County
and trying to turn that into a reality to meet the needs of your residents.
That's the benefit for you as a city by investing in this organization
and the work that you're doing on your own when it comes to economic development.
And also it helps to allocate those funds in a positive way
to increase business activity, job retention and creation.
And one of the things I know that you always want to talk about.
It helps to improve physical sustainability and that's the ultimate goal, because as you start
working, I think you just approved your budgets, I believe, already of this month or last
month, this was sustainability, it's important to everybody.
You want to know that not only are the budget numbers you're working on going to hold up,
but they're actually sustained from the year to year that they will continue to grow and
hopefully eliminate some of that rollercoaster ride that can happen sometimes with the city
budget.
We've also unit for more.
Another thing, another benefit of economic development, is that it focuses the community
on what shared long-term vision and it helps to create policies that enhance business
vitality and increase the standard of living, that I heard something today, I was in a
webinar this afternoon with Jim Fram, and I know that many of you don't know Jim Fram,
I know some of you do, just an amazing, amazing gentleman, especially with the field of
economic development.
He said, you know he said, the more people you can get involved in the planning process, the more people
you're going to get to buy in to the plant.
That's kind of what we're trying to do here with economic development through the economic
development service.
You're going to hear us talk a lot about working together with all of our partners to create
that vision.
We need my MS input to do that.
We need commerce, call, all, fairly, and why not, after the county, and of course, nothing gets
done if we don't work with our Native American partners as well.
They are a vital part of any economic development efforts that we're going to do here in
our county.
And another bit of it is that because you pull all of these public and private stakeholders
together, we're all working together for to bring them to increase and improve our current
businesses, but also to bring you new businesses, which means new job creation.
We want all of them to be successful, we want them all to thrive, and if we do our
partner put together a strong plan, we're going to make that happen.
So how do we speed that process up a little bit?
Well, there's a lot of things we need to do with the first thing we really need, and I know
some of you are talking about this on the city level, but we need a realistic vision for our
community.
I'm not just specifically talking about my M, I am, but I'm talking about the county as
a whole, because we're all in this, yeah, it's good for my M, it's good for the county.
And it's good for the county, my elbow will reach some benefit of that as well.
So when I say community, that's what I mean.
So for use specifically though, and both, I'd remember back in October.
I asked in these various, this very question, where do you see?
What's your plan?
Your vision for my Emma, five years from now?
What is it for 10 years?
20 years down the road?
And I would have the same conversation about having a team now
with all the part of the municipalities, the county, and our tribal partners.
Where do you see our community in 5 to 10, 15, 20 years down the road?
Well, it wasn't ready to answer that question or at that time.
I didn't say it thought about it, because he had it.
But he's still, I think, working on that vision is plan.
And you're starting to see some of that.
And you'll see them guide that through that process as you find it, too, that.
But that's a real thing.
We need to have that information.
We bring all of that.
We can help bring all of that information together.
To create one concise plan that everyone has had the involvement in.
Everyone can rally behind.
And hopefully it becomes a living, breathing document that we implement.
And we make positive things happen in our community.
So a lot of the things we need to do is we need to know
what our real resources are.
What are our assets?
And what are our infrastructure resources?
Who are our economic partners?
How's the real estate market in this area?
How deep and how wide is the talent pool?
Those are the kind of questions we need to know.
We need to know what that means in my end.
We need to know what that means in all of the other municipalities, the county, and what our tribal partners.
What are our resources?
Because those are the things that we, as an organization, will go out and sell from the communities we had.
That's how we do economic development.
We are the sales force for our economic development.
Well, it's a one-man show.
But we support the board because they're actually involved in everything that we do.
And then once we know our resources are, we start to shape that vision together.
Then we need to start thinking about who are our key individuals or organizations within our community.
That can help us get the word out about that shared vision so that we can help educate everyone in our community.
So that we can give them as excited about it as we are.
So they can help and be apart in the process.
Again, the more information you can take in, the more the community has involved in the process,
the more likely they're going to buy into it.
And that's what we need to do.
And so that's kind of what I wanted to update you on tonight, just to give you an example of the discussions that we're having on the organizational level.
These are the conversations that hopefully will be brought back to you as a council.
And hopefully that's going to take place in the other communities as well, because those are the things we're focusing on.
We'll go back to that first slide where I talked about those things that Heather mentioned back in May.
You know, every decision that we make, well, short of how to do things like by coffee pots or most kind of things.
But every decision we make in regard to how we're going to allocate our key resources, time, money, energy, everyone of those decisions should be able to be traced back to one of those six initiatives.
You do the same thing on the council level.
But what's going to come up with this vision from IMA with your input.
And you guys are going to set some strategic initiatives. Probably are in working on that.
And the same challenge that we have as an organization to trace everything back to those key statements you will have in every decision you may as a council.
You need to be able to say, okay, but how does that decision line up with our strategic initiative?
Does it support anything that we agree is important to us as a council?
We've got a great board in place. If you don't know who that board is, there is a slide.
There we go.
Our executive, of course, we're led by the amazing Chief Ethel Cook.
She's our chairperson. Our coosob is our vice chairperson.
Heather Lillard is our secretary of treacher. She'll serve as his past chairman.
And then you can see the other members in there. Jason Blethens, Brett Hayes, and they passed me.
I submitted Dr. Cal Stackard, Pat Jervens Martin.
And then you, as a city, you are represented on the board by two individuals city manager, Boe Rees,
and then Amanda Davis, and your director, of course.
Some of you may not know everything about me.
But if you need to get in the home with me for anything, my contact information is there.
You are free. You'll reach out to me at any point with any questions regarding economic development.
If you get a phone call from someone who is interested in my Emma, and maybe someone to talk to, send them our way.
More than happy to take that phone call.
We want my Emma and our local county to be successful.
I can't do it by myself. You can't do it by yourself.
But if we all work together for one day.
common goal. We can make it happen. The challenges are there. We all know we got lots of
challenges and if we focus on those challenges, they'll always be there. They'll always
be an obstacle. But there are great opportunities in all our account. Only only if we
continue to work together. Thank you so much for the continued support that this is
this council has shown to the minimari economic development service, literally couldn't
function without your assistance. And we need you to know that. And we need to know
how much we appreciate that. And hopefully, that's a relationship that we're going to
be able to continue for a long time. Not to have to answer any questions you have.
Your last sentence had a key word in it. Relationships. Your two previous predecessors
failed at that miserably. Not being ugly, not calling names, or nothing as disfacts. One of
your strengths I feel will be building those relationships with our business owners. So
that you actually know what they need and have a feel for it. And that'll allow you to give us
feedback about things we need to do to help drive that. Pounds this size can't always by their
way to prosperity, but they can relationship their way to some prosperity. And I think
on that front that you were the absolute right person for this job at this time.
Well, I appreciate that. That's something that I feel strongly about because those are partnerships.
No, most of you. Hopefully, much all of you can talk to us about all of you at one point or
another. I know that's important to you. I certainly know it's important to our board because
again, it all starts with those handshits and starts with getting to know those individuals all
of the players. Again, what are our assets? Who are our economic partners? You're not going to
determine that if you don't even involve and you don't get out and meet with people and build
relationships. So it's a task, but it's a responsibility that I've set to learn.
I know Monday afternoon, we've been working with a local manufacturer that's looking to expand here.
I'm also expanding here. We've been working with them for two or three months. And I got to
hand that off to Shannon. I introduced him to the player and said, here you go. So he can take
that run with it and I have full confidence that he'll be able to get this deal closed for us.
is everything that you'd like to know to develop, right?
Let's call it the editors.
For something totally unrelated.
And he said, what you did on that, and I said,
I'm getting ready to send you a lot of that.
Very individual, just touch a basin, introducing myself
to him.
Let's hang on a second.
Man, phone call.
And then I got, and I will be talking with him in a minute.
It's promising.
And you know, I know that a lot of times,
you guys want us to come up here and be very specific
about things that we're working on.
I hope that you all understand that
would it come to economic development?
There's a level of confidentiality there that has to be maintained.
And so, you know, trust me, when the time is right,
you'll be a person.
It's successes we have.
We want you to celebrate.
I mean, I want you to celebrate.
I want it's whole town.
It's whole town.
It's all right.
Any other questions?
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Chancellor.
Number seven.
Budget amendments.
We're doing number 22-30.
MCVV.
And then we'll do 22-31 demo.
The extra items for the 266, I think it's the missing ones.
And the shade structure.
We're moving money from general fund to the CV.
Because the budget is now in the CV.
It was in the general fund.
So you're talking $2548.
Is that going to do it?
Or are we going to be back to another amendment?
We were very moving in time.
We proceed.
But the rest of it got put in capital.
After July 1st.
Our additional table of chairs.
So this will get us to the first.
Yep.
You need these approved separately.
Okay.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Okay.
The other one.
The next one is on the theme of grant that we receive.
You're going to see four agenda items.
This is going to present those for those for the health.
Do you see them?
The money in the end.
Go ahead and skip.
Is this the businesses that we are going to vote on?
Or is this some separate?
This one.
Great partial billables.
And one of the bills.
Yeah.
So it's the ones that we've already passed.
Our demo.
There were actually buying but this is actually we we have to purchase the properties
We accept it the bid on the demos is what we've done. There's another house on there that
Yeah, there's
There's eight more houses in this
Yes, not in this this one has four and one occupied like that
So this this has
Thirsty big daddy's and a Thunderbird plus a house
Have the residential properties been bid on the turn-on yet. Only two of them have
Is the one in here one of them?
Yeah, this so 15
Scarquette Stack Harbor is kind of off on its own and then
24B
Southwest is kind of off on its own and then one do some different separately and then we'll come back to you with eight
together and those are all the ones located on it
So they're they're all three together and pick those
That else out east
But that one's done
Also
One of three L-Southie 23 23
Thank you.
I'm ready to contract with TSPI for utility bill, printing, and mailing.
So if you remember at your last initiative, I mean,
Cali informed you that you would see this on the council agenda,
because the contract has both the MSU and the council.
The city side, because the city side also uses TPSI,
for things like billing in, in terms of that terminology,
and kind of things like that.
So this is just a housekeeping manner to approve TPSI,
as well as to build printer, and things like printer,
on the same side.
Let me make a motion to approve.
Parker?
Hi.
December.
Davis?
Hi.
Thank you.
Nine.
Resolution CC 2022.
Dash of your nine.
Certification of my local home, a code of ordinances,
to include supplement 15.
This is what we do twice a year to get our ordinance books.
When you say up to date, explain that.
They take all the ordinances that we've passed in the last,
generally, about six months, and actually put it in the book.
Okay.
I think that's the first, but it all in the book.
Motion to approve.
Seven.
Simultimate.
December.
Davis.
E.C.
Parker.
Ten.
Remember, random of understanding between the city of my,
and all of the kind of fair board for the use of the fairgrounds,
show barons for the fiscal year 2022.
23.
As you can see, I'm not a student.
Kevin Hillenburg.
Officially resigned, and last day, we'll be in this way.
So 15 years.
You can finally just say, you know, I don't want to present.
So.
So that's a lot.
This is really just an housekeeping issue with the fair board.
It's something that would renew every year.
It has been presented approved at the last parks board.
If there's any highlight in this demo, you would all,
nothing's changed in the last year.
We'll just want everybody to know that.
The fair board is one of the few in low use.
It's not the only way that pays for all utilities for every event they have.
So whether it's a hall show or it's a fair weekly out there,
you can leave here's the four and a after.
We'll fill them in a tight time.
So.
All right, thank you Kevin. 11, purchase 1030 east southwest of the sum of 131,384 dollars and 85 cents.
That's part of the FEMA grant, 4438-year-16 acquisition, demolition grant, and accordance with the hazardous
mitigation plan.
As a reminder on all of this, this is a 75-25 match grant, so 75% of this money that we're spending
will come back to us as a reimbursement as part of this grant.
So our part that will be out that it's going to be done in any kind of services
25%. We are scheduled to close on the properties tomorrow that will present you today.
What's the properties closed and receive all the documentation that we need to receive from the
demolition contractor, the contractor will have 45 days to get the structures down.
And when the structures is the slab and everything?
Yeah, yes, and then we can't.
So on this one in particular, big daddies, we start to come back to you with a technically real part
of that. So that's still part of this that's coming back to you guys on this one in particular.
I can see what he was calling me every week, however weak one in the way we're out on this now.
Yeah, yeah, the difference in just for quickly and some of the pricing because there's a lot of different
bunch of relations has to deal with repellent losses and if they had insurance or not, that comes off
the value of the whole business, whichever it is. So we need to claim that comes off the dollar now.
You said one of them was occupied?
15, 12. We won't close with the occupied, we won't close with the occupied, we won't close on it.
We don't have 30 days to get out. And then once they are out of the property, which I don't think
it will take them that long to think it would. We think it would. We think it would call us our
congressmen have been taking office when this is going to happen on this property once he's out
in the list. So the plan with these properties are just turned on the grass.
That's what it'll be in the deed that will be redeveloped.
There's a possibility at some point these two commercial properties
over by the backgrounds who might turn those into parking lots
as long as we don't change the elevations at all.
I know that's something that we could do there.
They're like the rest of the most of El Southeast has been returning
to just lots.
It's just grass and all of Scotty Court.
This is all part of that thing.
So these properties are something else.
Kevin's going to have to take care of it.
Or what?
Unfortunately, all of this.
But we're looking at creating ways.
We all do.
But to manage that.
It's, yeah, it's a pair of dots in there.
I'm trying to be really kind of together.
I'm not getting any more properties that we're getting in the studio.
Let's get in the goat business.
Yeah.
There's a lot of things.
Kevin's here.
You're a random control too, aren't you?
I don't know.
I have to let him in.
Honestly, with the bad situation for the people in the properties
and then it's also a tough situation for the city.
I should also point out to you that the Western most two feet
that the big day is outside of the city limits.
But we're lying in it.
We can't leave it on the two foot strip.
You know.
What's that two foot worth?
Well, that concrete that brings up an interesting conversation to me.
Big daddy's.
There is concrete and a fair amount of that lot.
And if we hold true to form, we're going to pay somebody to tear it up
just so that we can put it back later.
Thank you.
Yeah.
So thanks.
Thank you, Arthur.
Thank you.
Come on, man.
I'm down.
He's on my side.
We're trying to take turns.
I'm down.
Motion to approve.
Take it.
Davis.
All right.
Thank you.
Twelve.
Part just 1130 east southwest.
For the sum of 31,832 dollars and 54 cents.
That's part of the theme of grant.
4438-016 acquisition, demolishing grant, and according to the Hadadist mitigation plan.
I'll make a motion to approve.
Pardon?
Aye.
Stunberg.
Davis.
Don't go.
Aye.
13.
Purchase 1603.
E.C. runs Boulevard for the song 503,592 dollars and 603 cents.
That's part of the same FEMA grant.
Second.
Stunberg.
Aye.
Don't go.
14.
Purchase 1512 Sky Harbor Drive for the song of $100,848 dollars.
That's part of the same FEMA grant acquisition and demolishing grant.
So, folks, do you step back?
Aye.
Thank you.
15.
New business of any of which is a business that's supposed to be this agenda.
16.
Staff reports.
17.
Mayor and council community analysis.
18.
Mayor, mayors of the council.
I wanted to take a minute to brag on our mayor a little bit.
So, last week.
I believe it's last week.
Or maybe before.
Mike Fena, the executive director of the Oklahoma Municipal League, reached out to Mayor Parker.
To inform him that he had been nominated by the mayor's council of Oklahoma.
nominating committee.
To fill a seat on their court for district one.
And after what I understand to be, a lot of consideration, rightly so, on his time.
And we're in terror on his family.
He accepted the nomination.
And I believe today it was formalized.
And his appointment was confirmed by the committee.
To serve in that capacity of district one.
And just so you all know, this, the mayor's council was formed in 1991.
And as a bipartisan organization to represent the concerns.
In views of the body of the state states mayors.
MCO as its known provides a vehicle for the development and implementation.
Of programs of multi jurisdictional cooperation between cities and towns designated to lessen the burden on local government.
Oklahoma mayors make the commitment to work through the comfort.
The conference to improve their own communities, as well as the conditions facing cities and towns.
out the state in nation. It was interesting the email in which they had reached out to bless,
had a line in there that I thought I should read. It said, the leadership you have demonstrated
in your own community has impressed the MCO board and they believe you would be a great fit for this
organization. So anyway, I just wanted to bring that all to your attention and brag on our mayor
minute about this great opportunity once again to insert my Emma on a state stage and I think our
mayor parker can make a significant difference on our behalf. So congratulations.
19 this meeting will be continued for the council chambers and we can meet in the staff room
for the purpose of the executive session.
How did you think we're done? I think you're still upstairs.
And that would be the staff or the council chambers and we'll vote on the two things we talked
about in the executive session. The first one will be the IAFF local 1969 contract.
Estep.
Hi.
Sumber.
So cool.
Upside.
Davis.
Hi.
Parker.
The next one will be the turn of order.
Please.
Davis.
Sumber.
Hi.
Estep.
Parker.
Hi.
Member.
Troy.
3.
General.
So moved.
Second.
Estep.